<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Digital Scholarly Edition: J.D. Salinger on Artistic Integrity, A Letter to
               Garson Kanin (1957) </title>
            <author>Jerome David Salinger</author>
            <editor>Dimitrios Chrysovalantis Mouzakitis, Riccardo Contin, 882098, 883467,
               908084</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Class Assignment</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement>New York City, New York, United States of America</settlement>
                  <repository>Bonhams</repository>
                  <idno>Lot 196</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <title type="original" xml:lang="en">A Letter Jerome David Salinger to Garson
                        Kanin (1957)</title>
                     <textLang mainLang="en">American English</textLang>
                     <argument>
                        <p>Typed Letter Signed ("J.D. Salinger"), 1 p, 8vo, New York, May 29, 1957,
                           on New Yorker letterhead, to Garson Kanin, regarding adapting his stories
                           for the stage; together with typed carbon of Kanin's May 16, 1957 letter
                           to Salinger; housed together in custom clamshell box, with 1996
                           bookseller's receipt.</p>
                     </argument>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Typed Letter</p>
                  <objectDesc>
                     <p>The document is a typed letter, signed by J.D. Salinger, dated May 29, 1957,
                        and written on official New Yorker letterhead. It consists of one page,
                        measuring 8vo (approximately 8 x 5 inches), a standard size for personal and
                        business correspondence. The paper likely has a slightly aged appearance,
                        possibly with minor discoloration or creases due to its age. The letter
                        features typed text in a traditional typewriter font, with Salinger’s
                        signature handwritten in ink at the bottom. Given its provenance and
                        literary significance, the document is preserved in a custom clamshell box,
                        ensuring protection and archival quality.</p>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Jerome David</forename>
                  <surname>Salinger</surname>
                  <idno type="VIAF">17092</idno>
                  <note>J. D. Salinger (1919–2010) was an American writer best known for The Catcher
                     in the Rye, a novel that became a defining work of 20th-century literature. His
                     writing often explored themes of alienation, identity, and the struggles of
                     adolescence. In addition to his famous novel, he wrote several short stories
                     and novellas, including Nine Stories, Franny and Zooey, and Raise High the Roof
                     Beam, Carpenters and Seymour: An Introduction. Despite his literary success,
                     Salinger became increasingly reclusive, avoiding public attention and
                     publishing little after the 1960s. His influence remains strong, with his works
                     continuing to be widely read and analyzed.</note>
               </persName>
               <date when="1957-05-29">May 29th 1957</date>
               <placeName>New York, United States of America</placeName>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Garson</forename>
                  <surname>Kanin</surname>
                  <idno type="VIAF">111110545</idno>
                  <note>Garson Kanin (1912–1999) was an American writer, director, and playwright
                     known for his contributions to theater, film, and literature. He wrote and
                     directed several Broadway plays and collaborated with his wife, Ruth Gordon, on
                     classic screenplays such as Adam’s Rib and Pat and Mike. Kanin also authored
                     novels, memoirs, and non-fiction works, including Tracy and Hepburn, a
                     biography of Spencer Tracy and Katharine Hepburn. His sharp wit and
                     storytelling talent made him a significant figure in mid-20th-century American
                     entertainment.</note>
               </persName>
               <placeName>Oxford, New York, United States of America</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
         <settingDesc>
            <listPlace>
               <place>
                  <placeName>New York City, New York, United States of America</placeName>
                  <note>New York City played a significant role in the lives of both J. D. Salinger
                     and Garson Kanin. As a literary and cultural hub, the city influenced
                     Salinger’s writing, with its energy and alienation reflected in The Catcher in
                     the Rye. Kanin, deeply immersed in Broadway and Hollywood, thrived in its
                     artistic circles, writing and directing for the stage and screen. Both men,
                     though different in their careers—one a reclusive novelist, the other a vibrant
                     playwright and filmmaker—left lasting marks on American literature and
                     entertainment, with New York as a key backdrop to their creative
                     journeys.</note>
               </place>
               <place>
                  <placeName>Oxford, New York, United States of America</placeName>
                  <note>Oxford, New York, is a historic town nestled in the heart of Chenango
                     County, established in 1792. The town played a significant role during the
                     early development of the region, with its location along important trade routes
                     contributing to its early growth. It was once a hub for agricultural activity,
                     particularly for its production of grain, which was transported along the
                     nearby Chenango Canal.</note>
               </place>
            </listPlace>
         </settingDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <watermark>THE NEW YORKER NO.25 WEST 43RD STREET, NEW YORK, 36, N.Y.</watermark>
               <date>May 29, 1957</date>
               <address>
                  <settlement> Oxford, 5-1414</settlement>
               </address>
               <salute>
                  <persName>Dear Mr. Kanin</persName>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I'm afraid what you've heard is very true—I don't see any of my fictional characters
               in the theater—but I'm glad you liked ZOOEY, and glad you thought and bothered to
               write. My stand about the theater isn't a very happy one, considering that there are
               so many fine people putting on plays—I'm thinking especially of Elia Kazan whom I
               like very much—but I have an old and unshakable notion that I know what's best for my
               characters. Thank you, though. Sincerely,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <persName>J.D. Salinger</persName>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
